<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity and reward of a willing mind a sermon preach'd at Exon before an assembly of ministers of the counties of Devon and Somerset, April 16, 1693 / by John Bush.</title>
            <author>Bush, John, fl. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15562608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15562608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1587:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity and reward of a willing mind a sermon preach'd at Exon before an assembly of ministers of the counties of Devon and Somerset, April 16, 1693 / by John Bush.</title>
                  <author>Bush, John, fl. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mich. Hyde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 23 misnumbered 21.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 32.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, IX, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Duty.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103757:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Neceſſity and Reward OF A Willing Mind.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at EXON before An Aſſembly of Miniſters Of the Counties of <hi>Devon</hi> and <hi>Somerſet, <hi>April</hi>
               </hi> 16. 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN BUSH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mich. Hyde</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Exon.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103757:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103757:2"/>
            <head>To my Brethren the Miniſters of the Counties of <hi>Devon</hi> and <hi>Somerſet,</hi> allowed by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and others that read this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough in the enſuing diſcourſe I treat of the neceſſity of a <hi>Willing Mind</hi> to the acceptable performance of our Duty, I muſt confeſs I was not (if I could have handſomly avoided it) very willing to Preach to ſuch an Aſſembly, much leſs to Print the Diſcourſe: I have done both at your requeſt, becauſe I took it as a Command which I could not but Obey; and yet knowing how unfit I was to do either, I thought that an excuſe for my Unwillingneſs, notwithſtanding which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to give a due ſubmiſſion to your Judgment; without that I ſhould declin'd both the one and the other: the true Reaſon why I choſe to ſpeak to this ſubject, was becauſe I found in my ſelf a great defect of this diſpoſition, and I conſidered it might be ſo with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters as well as my ſelf, and in ſtirring up you to the Willing and Chearful Performance of your Duty, I hoped to warm my ſelf by the ſame Fire which I was to make for others: if in what I have done, I may but ſerve as the ſmall Wood to kindle the Fire, 'tis as much as I deſigned. I am afrayd we are not enough thankful to God and the Government for the peaceable exerciſe of our Miniſtry, which is not given us upon a deſign (as formerly) by a Prince that did what he did in this matter to exalt his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, aad to trample upon the laws in order to bring in Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but by a Prince that hath adventured to ſhew kindneſs to an afflicted depreſſed party, in the Face of thoſe that ſeem to envy us this kindneſs, as much as ever the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> did their Father <hi>Jacobs</hi> to their Brother <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Surely all things conſidered
<pb facs="tcp:103757:3"/> our Liberty to attend our Duty in Peace and Quietneſs is one of the greateſt Inſtances of a Divine project baffling the Counſels of Men, that hath hapned in our days in this Nation; for hereby that is given by Law, which ſome Men never Intended to ſuffer, much leſs to Eſtabliſh; behold in this the Wiſdom of God that hath ſo circumſtantiated our Liberty, that now it ſeems to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven with the Intereſt of the Government, ſo that who ever declares himſelf an Enemy to the former, will hardly be thought a hearty Friend to the latter. And We ſhall never expreſs a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſenſe of this Mercy of God to us without a more chearful performance of our Duty, in ſubmiſſion to our preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; Diſcouragements will never excuſe us in the worſt of times, much leſs now, whilſt we have what the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> never liv'd to ſee; for they only had the future reward, but we with that the allowance of the Law, and by that means a freedom from trouble, a mercy which whilſt we wanted we valued more than now we ſeem to do.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe as 'tis Printed varieth not from what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, at leaſt from what I deſigned to deliver: I have added nothing to, nor omitted any material paſſage that I found in my Notes. The Lord give us all more of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Willing Mind, that we may have the ſame Reward.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So Prayeth Your unworthy Brother in the Miniſtry. <hi>John Buſh.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Middleney,</hi>
                  <date>May <hi>13th. 1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103757:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Corinthians 9.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For if I do this willingly, I have a Reward: but if againſt my will, a Diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed to me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Defence that the Apoſtle makes for himſelf throughout the Epiſtle, and particularly in this Chapter, argues that there were ſome perſons (if not Miniſters) in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that did queſtion his Apoſtolical Power, beſides the reflection that they made upon his gifts, and practice; but the uncertainty as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, wherein the accuſation lay, maketh ſome places in this Chapter, and throughout the whole Epiſtle the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be underſtood; 'tis probable that part of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation lay in this, that the Apoſtle laboured with his hands as a ſecular perſon, and did not live as a perſon devoted to the Miniſtry, which ordinarily requires a man's whole time and thoughts; and conſequently that being a poor Mechanick, he diſparag'd his Office for the preſent, and muſt at laſt be maintain'd by the Charity of the Churches; and that in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to ſuch a liberal Contribution for the Saints at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he deſign'd to have a ſhare of it to his own uſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baxter</hi> in locum.</note> ſomething of this nature was laid to his charge, beſides the reflection that they made upon his gifts, as being one that could make a ſhift to write, but not readily to expoſe his own thoughts; for ſo I underſtand the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103757:4"/> meaning of thoſe words, <hi>his bodily preſence is weak.</hi> As to the firſt of theſe, his Apoſtolical Power, he aſſerts it in the firſt Verſe of this Chapter; <hi>Am I not an Apoſtle? am I not free? have I not ſeen the Lord Jeſus?</hi> Shewing, that though he had not convers'd with our Saviour whilſt on Earth, (which was the ground of the Obiection, and ſeems to have ſome weight in it: For when the Apoſtles would ſupply the room of <hi>Judas,</hi> to make up the number twelve, according to the number of the twelve Tribes, they choſe one that had companied with them, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.21, 22.) yet notwithſtanding this, he was as much an Apoſtle as they, and that he had ſeen Chriſt in the way to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> when he receiv'd his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to be an Apoſtle, <hi>and that he was free, i. e.</hi> not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to one Perſon or Church more than to another upon a civil account, ſo as to beſtow his pains upon them for nought; and that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had leſs cauſe than other men to queſtion his Apoſtleſhip; for their Converſion was the Seal of his Office, <hi>viz. If I be not Apoſtle to others, yet doubtleſs I am to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the great caſe upon which the Apoſtle inſiſts for his Juſtification is about <hi>Maintenance,</hi> which the Apoſtle did not only not <hi>Receive,</hi> but <hi>Refuſe;</hi> and yet leſt his <hi>Refuſal</hi> ſhould be drawn into a <hi>preſident</hi> for the time to come, to the prejudice of a Settled <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> he takes the matter into conſideration, ſhewing, and that from the equitable part of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (which though a Law to <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth not oblige us Chriſtians, yet from the equity of that Law he proves) that ordinarily it is the duty of the People to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them that Preach to them: <hi>As they that miniſtred about the Temple and Altar,</hi> Levites and Prieſts, <hi>did live of the Temple and Altar; ſo they that Preach the Goſpel have a Right to live of the Goſpel; v.</hi> 13, 14. And yet becauſe that which in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral may be lawful, may not at all times, and to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103757:4"/> perſons be expedient, for this reaſon the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd the taking of Maintenance from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth; v.</hi> 15. <hi>I have uſed none of theſe things, neither have I written theſe things, that it ſhould be ſo done unto me; for it were better for me to die, than that any man ſhould make my glorying void;</hi> meaning that the ſucceſs of his Miniſtry which he calls his glory, was dearer to him than his Right to a Maintenance. And yet the Apoſtle would not be miſtaken, as if becauſe he was free from all men by Preaching <hi>Gratis,</hi> that therefore he thought himſelf at liberty to Preach, or not to Preach the Goſpel; no; <hi>neceſſity is laid upon me; Wo is unto me if I Preach not the Goſpel; v.</hi> 16. Now the Apoſtle having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the neceſſity of his duty, doth in theſe words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that diſpoſition of mind that is neceſſary to the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his Duty, ſhewing, that 'tis not the bare perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, but the willing performance that God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>If I do this willingly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that there is an Antitheſis in the words, though both parts of it are not expreſly mentioned; and in this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis there is a twofold Suppoſition, and a twofold Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the willing and chearful performance of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Apoſtle infers the certainty of his Reward; he doth not ſay, I ſhall have, but <hi>I have a Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſpeaks <hi>de preſenti,</hi> not that he expected the Reward here, but becauſe of its certainty, in which caſe we uſe to ſay, <hi>Sure pay is as good as ready Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From the unwilling performance of his duty he infers (but 'tis by Implication) the Loſs of the Reward, adding, that notwithſtanding his unwilling mind, if ſuch a frame ſhould return upon him, he would check it with the ſenſe of his duty; <hi>A diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed to me;</hi> as if he had ſaid, I muſt Preach the Goſpel, 'tis committed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103757:5"/> to me; were I not therefore better do it willingly, and be rewarded, than with an unwilling mind, and ſo loſe or leſſen the future Reward? 'Tis true as ſome obſerved the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is tranſlated, <hi>willingly,</hi> ſignifies <hi>Injuſſus,</hi> to which the word, <hi>of my own accord,</hi> better anſwers; and yet I do not think that the Apoſtle did reckon that in ſo doing, Preaching without a Maintenance <hi>gratis,</hi> he did more than his duty was, <hi>abſolutely conſidered.</hi> This the Papiſts would have to be the ſenſe of the place, telling us that this, and ſome other Scriptures eſtabliſheth their <hi>Doctrine of Divine Counſels,</hi> which we are at liberty to refuſe or obſerve; for they make neither duty nor ſin: And yet if we obſerve them, we do <hi>ſupererrogate,</hi> and attain a ſtate of Perfection highly meritorious: Now I do not ſee how this place fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours them in the leaſt; for if the unwilling mind be a loſs of the Reward, then it muſt needs follow that the Apoſtle did no more than his duty (all things conſidered) was to do: For the ſcope of the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe ſeems to amount but to this, that though Miniſters in the general have a Right to Maintenance, as much as ever the Prieſts and Levites had to live by the Temple and Altar upon Tythes and Offerings (I ſay as much, though not in the ſame manner, the Apoſtle doth not prove it from the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law, but from the equitable part of the Law, and therefore doth not prove the ſame ſort of Maintenance) yet (notwithſtanding this, that 'twas in the general his Right) for ſome particular Reaſons it was his duty not to inſiſt upon his own Right; for (as one obſerves in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe) there is a great difference between an <hi>Univerſal Law,</hi> and a Man's Perſonal Obligations <hi>for ſome other Law,</hi> not <hi>oppoſing,</hi> but <hi>explaining</hi> that <hi>Univerſal Law,</hi> as is very evident in the caſe before us. In the general 'tis the duty of the People to maintain them that Preach to them; for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103757:5"/> ordinarily if the People do not perform their duty, the Miniſter can't perform his; and yet notwithſtanding this, a particular Miniſter may fall under a Perſonal Obligation not to expect this from the People, either when the People <hi>cannot do it,</hi> or when the Miniſter <hi>needs it not;</hi> but above all, when the taking of Maintenance is <hi>apparently</hi> an <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of the ſucceſs of his Miniſtry,</hi> which was the Apoſtle's caſe. Now in doing this no man ſupererrogates, or doth more than his duty. I ſhall not determine abſolutely that what was the Apoſtle's <hi>practice</hi> is any Miniſter's <hi>duty</hi> at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but am of Opinion, that to ſay the Apoſtle did more than his duty, is to favour the <hi>Popiſh Doctrine of Counſels,</hi> and to ſay, that though it was the Apoſtle's duty to do this, it can't be ours, is to preſcribe to Almighty God what our Circumſtances ſhall be, of which no Man is Maſter: And 'tis eaſie to prove, that notwithſtanding the Univerſal Law of God which determines our duty <hi>in the general,</hi> our <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Obligations</hi> do ariſe from our <hi>Perſonal Circumſtances:</hi> This therefore is the Apoſtle's Argument; he doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine directly any other Man's duty, but for himſelf he could not ſee how he could lawfully do otherwiſe, to ſtop the mouths of his Adverſaries, to promote the ſucceſs of his Miniſtry, and to obtain the future Reward; in relation to which he conſiders in the next verſe, <hi>What then is my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward?</hi> that is, what is the way to obtain the Reward? <hi>viz.</hi> making the Goſpel of Chriſt without charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if againſt my will, a Diſpenſation of the Goſpel is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me;</hi> the Tranſlators have put in a word which they thought to be the ſenſe of the Apoſtle, which is not in the Greek; for 'tis only thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with an Accuſative Caſe, <hi>I have received a Stewardſhip;</hi> or a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation is committed to me:</hi> And you muſt not imagine that this Truſt is committed to him, upon the condition of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103757:6"/> his unwilling mind; no, but rather the <hi>conditional</hi> hath the force of an <hi>Exceptive,</hi> which is not unuſual with the Apoſtle; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>And if Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin; i. e.</hi> though Chriſt be in you; ſo here, <hi>If againſt my will,</hi> though againſt my will; that is, I am ſtill under a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of doing my duty, willing or unwilling I may loſe my own <hi>Reward,</hi> but not deſtroy the <hi>Obligation</hi> to my duty.</p>
            <p>It is the former part of the words that I ſhall limit the Diſcourſe unto, in which I ſhall not ſo much conſider the Apoſtle's Circumſtances, as the diſpoſition of mind which he makes ſo neceſſary to his acceptance, under this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> That a willing mind in the performance of our duty, is highly neceſſary to our Acceptance and Reward. <hi>Or thus;</hi> Whoever would receive the Reward of well doing, had need to do it with a willing mind.</p>
            <p>I am ſpeaking to Miniſters, but I would diſcourſe of that which concerns others as well as them, and ſhall ſhew you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What that diſpoſition of mind is, which the Apoſtle makes ſo neceſſary to well doing, that all may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have this <hi>willing mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Shew its Neceſſity in the general to all Men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Miniſters above others ſhould have it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Draw ſome practical Inferences from the Propoſition, in relation to us all as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but eſpecially as <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This willing mind ſeems to conſiſt of two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A <hi>fixing</hi> of the <hi>Will</hi> that it may ſtick to its <hi>duty.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>chearfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi> in its <hi>performance.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Will</hi> muſt be <hi>fixed;</hi> without this nothing is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103757:6"/> done willingly. The great Controverſie of late hath been, who doth determine the Will, <hi>God</hi> by the <hi>Irreſiſtible Operation</hi> of his <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Man</hi> by making thoſe <hi>Operations</hi> to be <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual?</hi> In which Controverſie, whilſt <hi>ſome</hi> have given to Man more power than in truth is in him; <hi>others</hi> have gone into another extreme; thoſe that go in the former extreme, though otherwiſe very Learned Men, do ſo rarely mention the <hi>Supernatural Operations</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which are as neceſſary to <hi>deliver the Soul</hi> from the bonds of <hi>Sin,</hi> as to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe the Body</hi> from the power of the <hi>Grave</hi> at the laſt day; that as one ſaith of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> 'tis hard to call them <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> for they ſcarce deſerve to be called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> ſo of theſe Men 'tis hard to ſay that they Preach <hi>another Goſpel;</hi> for they ſeldom Preach <hi>any Goſpel;</hi> and yet ſome have erred on the other hand, as if <hi>God's Grace</hi> had ſo ſuperſeded Man's <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that there were nothing for us to do, but to look when <hi>God will do it,</hi> that we may ſit ſtill and <hi>do nothing.</hi> The truth lieth between theſe two extremes, which will the ſooner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear if you conſider, that they only are <hi>willing</hi> whom <hi>God doth make willing;</hi> and yet every Man that is <hi>truly willing,</hi> his <hi>heart</hi> doth ſtir him up to his <hi>own duty,</hi> and his <hi>own ſpirit</hi> doth <hi>make him willing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They only are willing whom <hi>God doth make willing;</hi> for 'tis his work to ſubdue the will, a work that <hi>needs</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> a God to do; the work is the greateſt manifeſtation of a <hi>Divine Power;</hi> Pſal. 110.3. <hi>Thy people ſhall be a willing people in the day of thy power, in the beauties of holineſs; from the womb of the morning, thou haſt the dew of thy youth.</hi> The words ſeem to relate to thoſe <hi>early</hi> and <hi>numerous</hi> Converſions which are recorded in the Acts of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> where you find <hi>thouſands</hi> at <hi>one Sermon</hi> converted to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which times are therefore called <hi>the womb of the morning,</hi> and <hi>the dew of Chriſt's youth;</hi> becauſe, as he that goeth forth in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103757:7"/> 
               <hi>morning</hi> is then <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> for his <hi>Labour,</hi> and the <hi>Young Man</hi> hath moſt <hi>agility</hi> of body to run the <hi>Race:</hi> So the Grace of God in the firſt publiſhing of it ſhould go forth with that <hi>power</hi> as is in the <hi>young</hi> for his <hi>Race,</hi> as is in a <hi>ſtrong</hi> Man for his <hi>Labour.</hi> Hence it is that they that think they have <hi>made themſelves willing,</hi> do but deceive themſelves, when by the <hi>Grace of God</hi> they were not <hi>made ſo;</hi> for the <hi>Will</hi> of Man is conquered by none but <hi>God;</hi> Men may attempt it, to <hi>bend</hi> it to God's Will, as you would <hi>bend</hi> a <hi>crooked</hi> Stick; it will return to its own <hi>crookedneſs.</hi> And therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> that knew what a great work 'tis to <hi>fix</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> to its <hi>duty,</hi> tells the People, that though they had ſeen more of God's Power than ever any Nation before them, or perhaps more than ever any Nation ſhall ſee whilſt the World continueth, if God would do this, they would ſee more of a <hi>Divine Power</hi> than as yet they had ſeen; <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.2, 3, 4. <hi>Ye have ſeen all that the Lord did before your eyes in the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>unto</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and his Servants, and to all his Land, the great temptations which thine eyes have ſeen, yet the Lord hath not given you an heart to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>work;</hi> and the <hi>ſucceſsleſneſs</hi> of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>means</hi> ſhews it to be <hi>God's work,</hi> and therefore to argue againſt this from ſome difficulties that occur in ſtating the Controverſies, as to the <hi>manner</hi> of the operation of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> upon our <hi>Wills;</hi> that becauſe Man hath a <hi>ſelf-determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Principle, and is <hi>Maſter</hi> of his own <hi>actions,</hi> which can't be denied; yet to argue from hence, that this can't agree with the <hi>Irreſiſtible Operations</hi> of God's <hi>Grace,</hi> is to pretend a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs to <hi>Human Nature,</hi> that we may not wrong that, and in the mean time wrong <hi>God,</hi> as if we were to be more tender of <hi>Man's Honour</hi> than of <hi>God's Honour:</hi> Why ſhould it not ſuffice us what ſo many have ſaid in this matter, that the turning of the Will is done by <hi>Moral Perſwaſion</hi> as Man is a <hi>Rational Creature,</hi> made for <hi>Moral Government;</hi> but the <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103757:7"/> of <hi>God's Grace</hi> lieth in the immediate <hi>Operations</hi> of <hi>God's Spirit</hi> upon Man's <hi>Will,</hi> which is ſubdued in a way of <hi>power,</hi> as Man is a <hi>wicked Creature,</hi> and yet ſo ſubdued, that no Man is <hi>forced</hi> againſt his <hi>Will,</hi> but made <hi>willing;</hi> and yet that which makes him ſo, is not the <hi>cooperation</hi> of his <hi>own Will</hi> with God's <hi>Spirit,</hi> but the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> over the <hi>Will,</hi> which being <hi>effectual,</hi> Man ſhall not be <hi>able</hi> to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> it; and if he <hi>could,</hi> he <hi>would not,</hi> he is ſo <hi>drawn</hi> by <hi>Love,</hi> as well as <hi>ſubdued</hi> by <hi>Power.</hi> Now to ſcorn all this, which in effect ſo many have done, by ſaying, How can this be, and Man act as a <hi>ſelf-determining</hi> Creature, <hi>Maſter</hi> of his own <hi>Actions?</hi> is to pretend that we can <hi>refine</hi> upon <hi>every thing</hi> that is done in the World; when in the mean time if we deſcend into the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>things,</hi> we can give account of <hi>nothing;</hi> for though we do all know that we can will, and chuſe, and refuſe, and think, and love, and hate, yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>how</hi> this is done, <hi>how</hi> the Soul, that is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> doth operate upon the <hi>Body,</hi> to <hi>move</hi> and <hi>ſtir</hi> it, and <hi>how</hi> one <hi>thought</hi> doth beget <hi>another,</hi> and who can give an account of all this? Why then ſhould we pretend to know <hi>how far</hi> the Spirit of God can operate upon our Souls to <hi>incline</hi> us to good, and not <hi>deſtroy</hi> that <hi>determining Principle</hi> which is in all Men? and therefore it will more become us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that which the Scripture is ſo poſitive in, though we can't give an account <hi>how</hi> 'tis.</p>
            <p>And, as I hinted before, there is not only need of God's Grace to <hi>determine</hi> the Will <hi>to</hi> its duty, but to <hi>keep</hi> it <hi>there:</hi> For we are apt to <hi>go off</hi> from our own <hi>Reſolutions</hi> and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes,</hi> and to loſe the preſent <hi>Impreſſion</hi> of God's Grace; the <hi>willing mind</hi> will of it ſelf become <hi>unwilling;</hi> and therefore God having <hi>tryed</hi> us in <hi>Adam,</hi> doth not <hi>truſt</hi> us in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Covenant</hi> to our <hi>ſelves;</hi> and we have need to conſider this, that we may not <hi>depend</hi> upon the <hi>firſt determination</hi> of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103757:8"/> our own <hi>Wills;</hi> we are <hi>mutable, fickle,</hi> and <hi>unconſtant</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; our <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>deceitful,</hi> not only in this, that they are not <hi>really willing</hi> when they <hi>ſeem</hi> ſo, but are ſoon <hi>chang'd</hi> from <hi>willing</hi> to be <hi>unwilling;</hi> and the true Reaſon why Men do not live more ſuitable to their <hi>own Reſolutions,</hi> is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were <hi>never willing</hi> but becauſe men do <hi>change their minds</hi> from <hi>willing</hi> to <hi>unwilling,</hi> for which reaſon 'tis that <hi>God</hi> deſclaimes his being like <hi>Man,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>lie</hi> or <hi>Repent;</hi> Men will <hi>promiſe</hi> what they never Intend to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form:</hi> this is lying with a witneſs; but beſides that, they that <hi>ſcorn</hi> to do <hi>this</hi> do <hi>Repent,</hi> that is <hi>change</hi> their <hi>minds, God</hi> is not <hi>ſuch</hi> an one, <hi>we will ſerve the Lord, ſaid</hi> the People, but <hi>you can't ſerve the Lord</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſhua,</hi> not that <hi>abſolutly</hi> they could not, but becauſe he ſaw in them a kind of <hi>raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>reſolve,</hi> but they did not enough conſider that <hi>to do</hi> what they <hi>promiſed</hi> there was more need of <hi>Gods Grace</hi> than as yet they were ſenſible of, and without <hi>this</hi> they <hi>could not ſerve the Lord</hi> and it is generally the <hi>miſtake</hi> of good men to think that they ſhall be <hi>able</hi> to do what they are <hi>willing</hi> to do, <hi>Peter</hi> found it ſo, <hi>David,</hi> whoſe heart was <hi>made willing,</hi> prays that it might be <hi>kept ſo.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. <hi>Who am I, and what is this People? that we ſhould be able to offer ſo willingly, keep this Lord for ever in the Imaginations of the thoughts of the hearts of this people, and eſtabliſh their hearts to thee;</hi> that is, thou haſt <hi>made</hi> us <hi>willing,</hi> Lord <hi>keep us ſo,</hi> the firſt grace to <hi>determine</hi> the <hi>will</hi> may be <hi>given,</hi> and that grace <hi>not given</hi> which is needfull to <hi>performance. He worketh to will and to do,</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>Paul</hi> found it <hi>ſo, to will is preſent with me, but how to perform I find not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet he only is <hi>willing</hi> whoſe <hi>heart</hi> doth <hi>ſtir</hi> him up, and whoſe <hi>Spirit</hi> doth make him <hi>willing,</hi> as 'tis ſaid of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Exod. 35.21, 29. <hi>and they came e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one whoſe heart ſtirred him up, and every one whoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103757:8"/> Spirit made him willing,</hi> verſe 29. the Children of Iſrael brought a <hi>willing</hi> offering to the Lord, every Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whoſe <hi>heart</hi> made them <hi>willing;</hi> it is the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>this</hi> that God complains of Iſa. 64.7. <hi>none ſtirreth up himſelf,</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would have <hi>Timothy ſtir up the gift in him,</hi> not only the <hi>Miniſterial,</hi> but the <hi>Sanctifying gift</hi> of Gods Grace, for though the <hi>Grace</hi> of God be not made <hi>effectual</hi> by our own <hi>co-operation</hi> with it, neither is it <hi>effectual</hi> without our own <hi>Concurrence,</hi> and therefore it is that we are directed to our duty towards Gods Grace, and that not only when we <hi>have it,</hi> but that we may <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it;</hi> not only to <hi>keep</hi> our ſelves <hi>awake</hi> when God hath <hi>awakned,</hi> but <hi>to awake out of ſleep that Chriſt may give us Life,</hi> Eph. 5.14. for 'tis the <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> in man that is the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all the <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil</hi> that is in man, and under Gods <hi>Grace</hi> the <hi>firſt mover: out of the heart proceeds Murder, Fornication and Adultery, and a good Man out of the good treaſure of the heart bringeth forth good things;</hi> as we are never <hi>ſubdued</hi> to <hi>Gods Grace</hi> till the <hi>will</hi> be <hi>ſubdued,</hi> ſo the <hi>will</hi> is <hi>never ſubdued,</hi> till it <hi>ſtirs us</hi> up to our duty. <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.10. <hi>when Wiſdom entereth into thy heart and knowledge is pleaſant to thy Soul,</hi> then the work ſucceeds, and never till then, for (as Mr. <hi>Fenner</hi> ſaith) <hi>ſincerity</hi> lieth in the <hi>Will.</hi> So that as he that would <hi>kindle</hi> the fire muſt <hi>put</hi> the Fewel together, and then <hi>Blow</hi> to it; So <hi>God</hi> working upon us <hi>as Rational Creatures,</hi> doth expect that we <hi>do</hi> what we <hi>may;</hi> towards our turning to Him; and this <hi>ſtirring</hi> up our Selves that our hearts may <hi>make</hi> us <hi>Willing,</hi> holds as to the <hi>firſt Grace</hi> by which the <hi>Will</hi> is <hi>determined,</hi> and as to that <hi>Subſequent</hi> grace, by which it is <hi>kept</hi> to its duty; and in both Reſpects is <hi>Oppos'd,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>Outward Judgments,</hi> and <hi>Foreign motives,</hi> which many a man is Influenc'd by, whoſe heart doth not make him
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103757:9"/> willing; and when 'tis ſo, the <hi>thing done,</hi> though otherwiſe <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Praiſe-worthy,</hi> hath no <hi>acceptance</hi> with God: for 'tis not done <hi>willingly,</hi> that is <hi>ſincerely: Jehu</hi> in his acceſs to the Throne of his maſter <hi>Ahab, pretended Zeal</hi> to the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in that pretended zeal pulled down the Altar and Images of <hi>Baal,</hi> and deſtroyed his Maſters houſe, and yet ſaith God (though <hi>Jehu</hi> did what he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded) <hi>I will avenge the blood of Jezreel upon the houſe of Jehu.</hi> The blood of that Woman as <hi>Bad</hi> as ſhe was, was <hi>too good</hi> to be ſpilt upon ſo <hi>low</hi> an <hi>end</hi> as <hi>Jehu</hi> purpoſed to himſelf; for it ſeems it was not <hi>Gods Glory,</hi> but his own <hi>ſecurity</hi> or <hi>Revenge,</hi> or <hi>both:</hi> the like may be ſaid as to <hi>cuſtom</hi> or <hi>example,</hi> the latter of which, though we may <hi>Lawfully</hi> make <hi>a good uſe</hi> of, yet when 'tis that only or <hi>Cheifly</hi> that prompts us to our Duty, It will never pleaſe God, and generally He <hi>is made Willing</hi> by <hi>foreign motives,</hi> the <hi>Praiſe</hi> or <hi>fear</hi> or the <hi>example</hi> of men that he may not ſeem <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, any thing elſe</hi> that is <hi>ſhort</hi> of <hi>Gods Glory,</hi> take away <hi>that,</hi> and He goeth no farther, as when you take away the <hi>weight</hi> that made the Clock <hi>go,</hi> it ſtoppeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And It muſt be in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the workings of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience enlightned,</hi> but not <hi>Renewed:</hi> for we may have a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our <hi>Duty</hi> when we have no <hi>Inclination</hi> to its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. I don't ſay but 'tis better to <hi>do</hi> what is <hi>good</hi> and to <hi>forbear</hi> what is <hi>Evil,</hi> though it be only the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our <hi>Duty,</hi> without a <hi>Willing mind,</hi> prompting us to it, and yet 'tis evident enough that this is a <hi>ſort of Religion,</hi> which none ſhould <hi>reſt</hi> in: conſcience when <hi>Enlightned</hi> but not <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> may put Men upon doing <hi>ſomething</hi> in Religion, which is far enough from what the Apoſtle calls <hi>Obeying from the heart;</hi> take a wicked Man at ſome <hi>Particular times,</hi> when he is under the Influences of <hi>Fear</hi> upon a <hi>Sick bed,</hi> and how <hi>free</hi> doth he <hi>ſeem</hi> to be from that <hi>rancor</hi> and <hi>prejudice</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103757:9"/> that before appeared in him? <hi>Now</hi> he is for an <hi>Holy Life, Reſolv'd</hi> on a <hi>ſudden,</hi> now he is for <hi>Prayers</hi> and perhaps <hi>thoſe Prayers</hi> which before he <hi>ſcoff'd at!</hi> What a change doth this ſeem to be? but yet this <hi>Work</hi> is but the <hi>Oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> of an <hi>enlightned awakned</hi> conſcience, <hi>melted, humbled</hi> under the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Gods Wrath;</hi> but yet as the metal when in the Fire was <hi>ſoft,</hi> when out of the Fire grows as <hi>hard</hi> or <hi>harder than</hi> before ſo do they that are only under the operation of <hi>fear, In their affliction they will ſeek me early, than they will cry, ariſe and ſave us.</hi> Jer. 2.26. 'tis <hi>Fear</hi> cheifly that works upon <hi>Conſcience</hi> when <hi>enlightned</hi> only, but not <hi>Renewed</hi> and <hi>Sanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore it is that when what they <hi>feared</hi> ſeems upon their Recovery to be at <hi>a diſtance</hi> from them, they <hi>fear</hi> it <hi>as little</hi> as before; for <hi>fear</hi> is not <hi>laſting;</hi> he whoſe <hi>Conſcience only</hi> doth <hi>ſtir him</hi> up to his Duty, will ſeek an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage one time or other <hi>to be at liberty</hi> from his <hi>fears:</hi> for he is as a man in Priſon that cannot go and do as he would, but an heart <hi>made Willing</hi> by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> and making <hi>us Willing</hi> is enlarg'd to its <hi>Duty;</hi> were there more of this <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of mind in us, there would be <hi>leſs</hi> need of the <hi>Reſtraints</hi> or <hi>Conſtraints</hi> of Conſcience, 'tis to be obſerv'd in the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the firſt ſetting up of the Tabernacle, their own hearts ſtirring them up, they did ſo forward the work that <hi>Moſes</hi> made a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation throughout the Camp, <hi>let no Man make any more work for the Tabernacle, and ſo the People were reſtrained.</hi> Exod. 36.6, 7. For want of this there is no need in any Publick work to reſtrain men from over doing; It were well if by any means men would be conſtrained to their Duty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This willing mind conſiſts in a <hi>chearfull performance</hi> of our <hi>Duty;</hi> he that can live under a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of his <hi>Duty,</hi> and can attain to a <hi>Reſolvedneſs</hi> to <hi>ſtick</hi> to its <hi>Performance,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103757:10"/> and in the <hi>performance</hi> can <hi>find</hi> in himſelf <hi>a chearfullneſs of mind,</hi> hath attain'd <hi>a good meaſure</hi> of that <hi>dipoſition of Spirit,</hi> which the Apoſtle makes ſo <hi>neceſſary</hi> to our <hi>acceptance</hi> and <hi>Reward:</hi> for where the <hi>Will</hi> is <hi>ſubdued,</hi> it doth carry with it the <hi>ſubordinate affections</hi> and ſo where the <hi>Will</hi> is, <hi>Love</hi> is, and where <hi>Love</hi> is, <hi>delight</hi> will be The great <hi>Promiſe</hi> of God is <hi>to write his Laws upon our hearts,</hi> now this writing the <hi>Law</hi> in the <hi>heart</hi> ſignifieth <hi>an act of Grace upon the Will towards Gods Law, rather than upon the underſtanding to know it:</hi> for the miſery of man lyeth not ſo much in an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of Gods <hi>Will,</hi> as in an <hi>enmity</hi> to <hi>it;</hi> now when God <hi>takes</hi> away this <hi>enmity,</hi> and <hi>puts</hi> a <hi>new byas</hi> into our <hi>Souls Love</hi> and <hi>delight</hi> will not only <hi>conſtrain</hi> us to <hi>Obedience,</hi> but will make it <hi>more or leſs Eaſy</hi> and <hi>Delightfull:</hi> Moſt things <hi>are to us</hi> as we ſtand <hi>affected to them,</hi> and therefore that is a <hi>delight</hi> to <hi>one,</hi> that to <hi>another</hi> is a <hi>burden;</hi> but now God in order to <hi>Reduce</hi> us to our <hi>Duty,</hi> doth give us <hi>diſpoſition ſuitable</hi> to it, and therefore when this <hi>Will of God</hi> meets with a <hi>diſpoſition ſuitable to it,</hi> 'tis <hi>this</hi> makes <hi>obedience Eaſie,</hi> and us <hi>chearfull</hi> in it, <hi>thy Law is in my heart, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do thy Will O God.</hi> Pſal. 40.8. So that he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>delight</hi> himſelf in the <hi>Almighty,</hi> nor in <hi>his Duty,</hi> is never like to <hi>perſiſt</hi> in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. I do not extend this ſo far as to exclude all thoſe from the Grace of God, that have not the <hi>Swavitys</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> thoſe <hi>ſenſitive Joys</hi> and <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> which are <hi>rather</hi> the <hi>Evidences</hi> of the <hi>full aſſurance</hi> of <hi>underſtanding,</hi> than of <hi>Grace</hi> in its <hi>lower degrees,</hi> but I ſpeak it in this ſenſe, that what we do in obedience to Gods <hi>Will muſt</hi> not be <hi>a burden</hi> to us: for what is <hi>a burden</hi> though for <hi>a time</hi> we may <hi>bear it,</hi> one time or other we ſhall <hi>lay</hi> it <hi>down,</hi> at <hi>leaſt</hi> we muſt be <hi>ſo far Reconciled</hi> to our <hi>Duty,</hi> that we had <hi>rather</hi> do it, than <hi>Neglect:</hi> for what we <hi>Do grudgingly,</hi> and had <hi>rather</hi> do <hi>otherwiſe</hi> though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103757:10"/> for ſome reaſons we <hi>do it,</hi> 'tis in the ſight of God as if we <hi>did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>neceſſity</hi> of this <hi>diſpoſition</hi> will appear if you conſider two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>No good</hi> in an <hi>Ordinary way</hi> will be done <hi>without</hi> it, to <hi>do</hi> is more than to <hi>Will</hi> in ſome reſpect. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> found it ſo, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not <hi>abſolutely</hi> deny a <hi>Power Imparted</hi> to him for the doing Good; for I beleive he <hi>ſpeaks</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> as <hi>renewed</hi> by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> but he compares <hi>doing</hi> and <hi>Willing,</hi> and tells us he found it eaſier to <hi>Will</hi> than to <hi>perform;</hi> now if where the <hi>Willing</hi> mind <hi>is,</hi> a <hi>Power</hi> to do may be <hi>wanting,</hi> It will be much more ſo, where the <hi>Willing Mind</hi> is <hi>not,</hi> I know where the <hi>Willing Mind,</hi> which is <hi>firſt</hi> in order of nature, is vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed the <hi>Tower to Perform</hi> ſhall be <hi>given</hi> in <hi>ſome meaſure,</hi> yet It muſt needs be that where that which is firſt in order of Nature and not <hi>obtain'd,</hi> that which depends upon it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>expected,</hi> for as in going up the Ladder you muſt begin at the loweſt range, ſo in order to <hi>acceptable Obedience,</hi> we muſt begin at the <hi>Willing Mind;</hi> the reaſon why the Stony ground brought not forth any thing to perfection, was this it had no <hi>depth of Earth to cheriſh the Seed,</hi> ſo is all <hi>Obedience</hi> without an <hi>heart</hi> made <hi>Willing;</hi> either it will not be <hi>at all,</hi> or it <hi>Will wither,</hi> as the Graſs upon the houſe top, wherewith the Mower filleth not his hands</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Willing Mind</hi> doth <hi>ſo forward</hi> men to that which <hi>tends</hi> to <hi>Gods Glory,</hi> and the <hi>Good of others,</hi> that this may convince us of its <hi>neceſſity;</hi> thus then the perſon pleads not <hi>excuſes,</hi> layes aſide his <hi>delays,</hi> is exalted above <hi>Diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and ordinarily we may <hi>expect aſſiſting Grace</hi> to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,</hi> when by the grace of God we are <hi>Inclin'd</hi> to our <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We are apt to <hi>excuſe our</hi> ſelves out of our <hi>Duty,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103757:11"/> the general <hi>excuſe</hi> of wicked Men is, they <hi>Cannot;</hi> but the <hi>True</hi> Reaſon is our <hi>want of a Will:</hi> if men were <hi>really</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (as Mr. <hi>Fenner</hi> obſerves) they would <hi>do</hi> what they <hi>can,</hi> but when men can do ſomething, at leaſt <hi>frame</hi> their doings that they may turn to the Lord, <hi>conſider,</hi> that they may <hi>Repent, hear,</hi> that they may <hi>conſider</hi> and <hi>attend</hi> the <hi>word of God,</hi> and the <hi>places of his Worſhip,</hi> where they may <hi>hear</hi> their <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>know</hi> their <hi>danger,</hi> 'tis evident that men can do this; what ſhould hinder them? Now when men <hi>can</hi> do this and yet <hi>will</hi> not, and then pretend <hi>excuſes,</hi> how Juſtly may God Condemn ſuch perſons? an heart made Willing layes aſide excuſes, there <hi>is no Lion in that Mans way;</hi> pleading excuſes argues, that there is at the preſent a <hi>conteſt</hi> within as to our <hi>Duty,</hi> whither we <hi>ſhall</hi> or <hi>no,</hi> and ſo far as we <hi>Cleave</hi> to our <hi>excuſes,</hi> ſo far we <hi>take</hi> part with <hi>Sin,</hi> againſt <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Conviction,</hi> for the <hi>deſign</hi> of <hi>Conviction</hi> is to put us <hi>forward,</hi> but the deſign of <hi>excuſes</hi> is to <hi>draw</hi> us out of the hands of Mercy. An heart made willing, as far as 'tis really willing, lays aſide its excuſes. <hi>Peter</hi> had an <hi>Excuſe,</hi> in appearance a <hi>good one, we have toiled all Night, and taken nothing, nevertheleſs at thy word I will caſt in the Net.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Willing Mind</hi> will not be <hi>put off with delays,</hi> 'tis ſaid, that <hi>he that believeth will not make haſte,</hi> but 'tis meant of the <hi>thing Promiſed</hi> and <hi>Expected,</hi> in relation to which he that <hi>Believeth</hi> will <hi>wait,</hi> and not <hi>precipitate</hi> the <hi>Counſell</hi> of God, nor the <hi>accompliſhment</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe</hi> either <hi>before</hi> its <hi>time,</hi> or in an <hi>unlawfull manner;</hi> but in Relation to our <hi>Duty,</hi> the <hi>ſooner,</hi> generaly the <hi>better;</hi> for we may ſet about it <hi>too late,</hi> but ſeldom or never <hi>too ſoon.</hi> So that he that <hi>is really Willing</hi> to turn to God, doth <hi>determine</hi> to do it <hi>preſently, deferring</hi> to <hi>hereafter</hi> is the fruit of <hi>an unwilling Mind.</hi> Pro. 3.27, 28. <hi>Withhold not good from him to whom it is due, when it is in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103757:11"/> the Power of thy hands to do it, Say not to thy Neighbour go and come again, and to Morrow I will give, when thou haſt it by thee.</hi> The Wiſe Man conſidered that <hi>delaying</hi> is not <hi>ſafe,</hi> for we may either <hi>looſe</hi> the <hi>Opportunity</hi> of doing, or, which is worſe, the <hi>Will</hi> to <hi>perform,</hi> the <hi>preſent Impreſſion</hi> as well as the <hi>preſent opportunity</hi> may be gone by <hi>delaying</hi> without a good cauſe, we make no <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Command</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to <hi>the Time,</hi> and to <hi>Morrow</hi> we may make no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Command</hi> that relates to the <hi>thing</hi> it <hi>ſelf.</hi> The Apoſtle whom God at an <hi>Inſtant</hi> Inclin'd to his Duty, did <hi>immediately</hi> ſet about it, Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15, 16, 17 <hi>But when it pleaſed God, who ſeparated me from my Mothers Womb, and call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me by his grace to reveal his Son in me, that I might Preach him among the eathen, immediately I conferred not with fleſh and Blood.</hi> And therefore it muſt needs be a general miſtake in the World for men to pretend that they are not only <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced</hi> that 'tis their Duty to lead a new Life, but <hi>Willing,</hi> and yet this <hi>muſt not be</hi> till <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet think it ſhall be well enough, eſpecially if it ſhould happen that they live to that hereafter; 'tis true in ſome caſes and as to ſome particular dutys, It may conſiſt with a willing mind to defer them, when the preſent time is not convenient, or when the time to come may prove more advantagious; but as to the amendment of a Mans life, to pretend to be willing, but not for the preſent, as in it ſelf 'tis not a real willingneſs, ſo in ſome reſpect 'tis a reſolution to the contrary of what we pretend to, and therefore how can ſuch a purpoſe be pleaſing to God? conſider that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the danger that you run, and the preſumption that you manifeſt, that the grace and Mercy of God, nay, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall be at your beck, when you ſhall be at leiſure to return to him you do at preſent reſolve that as yet you will not as if you had not enough provoked the Almighty as if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103757:12"/> the time paſt of your Life did not ſuffice you to have wrought wickedneſs, but you will continue to do ſo longer; you do in effect declare that you ought to live otherwiſe, than you have done, that you muſt do otherwiſe, and be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of perſons, and yet though you have wronged God already, and wearied the Almighty, and though if you die in your Sins without repentance you expect dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and though you have no aſſurance that God will give you longer time, as to be ſure you have not yet, you will venture upon it, you will run the hazard of being damned, under a pretence that you will do your Duty hereafter, when you have ſpent your time in Sin, and can do God no Service; when you can Sin no longer, you will ceaſe to do Evil, and when you can do nothing, then you will learn to do well; when the day is at an end, you will go forth to your Labour, and when the Sun is ſetting then you will ſet forth for your Journey; can this delaying conſiſt with a willing mind;</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for <hi>diſcouragements, this diſpoſition of mind will help us to overcome them.</hi> In the beſt of times well doing will meet with if not direct oppoſition at leaſt diſcouragements, for whilſt the World continueth, the Seed of the Serpent which ſprung up in <hi>Cain</hi> will be, The World will be ungrateful, malicious and oppoſit to what is good; even <hi>Morality</hi> hath had its <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> much more ſhall all they <hi>that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> the greateſt Innocence, the ſtricteſt life, the moſt publick Spirit, the utmoſt caution ſhall never be able at all times and in all places, to protect the Servants of God from the tongues or hands and hatred, of the wicked, who rather than they will loſe the opportunity of doing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheif, will turn Chriſtians, that under the pretence of the Chriſtian name they may wreak their Malice upon them, that differ not from them, but in thoſe things wherein they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103757:12"/> themſelves differ from what they pretend to; theſe men will ſhew a Reverence to the deceaſed Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Saviour, that they may miſchief the living ones, Nay ſometimes perſecute them for that very thing, for which the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Lord are reverenced among Chriſtians; Juſt ſo the <hi>Jews did build and adorn the Sepulc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers of the Prophets whom their fathers ſlew,</hi> and <hi>did to the Diſciples what their fathers did to the Prophets;</hi> Now this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of mind will help us againſt theſe diſcouragements, for 'tis our unreſolvedneſs that makes the diſcouragements that lye in our way, more and greater than they are.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Where this is, we may <hi>expect Gods aſſiſting Grace to help us to do what by his Grace we are Inclined to,</hi> for though willing and doing are not equally eaſy, yet if we humbly go to God under the ſenſe of our Duty, and do not lean too much to our own Reſolutions, God will not be wanting to us, his Grace ſhall be ſufficient for us, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Being confident of this very thing that he that hath begun a good work in you, will perform it untill the day of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> 'tis true, God keeps this grace in his own hands, but yet the giving of the firſt grace doth give us cauſe to depend upon him for this alſo, which we ſhall be ſure to obtain, if we do not forfeit it by our neglects. I ſay again, where this willing Mind is in truth, It will cauſe that we ſhall not be Barren nor Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful in the knowledg of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for the Kingdom of <hi>God</hi> doth not conſiſt in Word but in Power, nor in wiſhing and willing, but in doing and performing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Having ſhewn in the <hi>general</hi> the <hi>neceſſity of this diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind,</hi> I would more <hi>particularly</hi> conſider it as 'tis <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Miniſters,</hi> to whom whilſt I am ſpeaking I would not be thought to pretend to ſpeak what they can't tell me, as well as I do them, but only to put them in Remembrance of what they all know.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103757:13"/>1. Therefore we all know and therefore ſhould conſider that the <hi>bare Art of Preuching, as a task expected at our hands every Lords-day, can never pleaſe God, but the Mind with which this and every other part of our Duty is perform'd.</hi> God is a great God, and a good Maſter, and therefore a little forc'd ſervice without our Wills, or againſt our Will, done becauſe we dare not for ſhame do otherwiſe, can this be Accepted and Rewarded? 'tis ſaid in the general there muſt be <hi>a Willing Mind, and then God accepts men according to what they have and can do, and not according to what we have not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot do,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. This muſt be firſt in all men, and firſt in us Miniſters above other men; Our work is ſo great in turning Men from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of <hi>Satan</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> that no Man is ſufficient for it, and yet notwithſtanding our inſufficiency for the work, and our lame defective Performance of our Duty, <hi>God</hi>'s declared readineſs to accept our endeavours and to Pardon our defects, ſhould at leaſt convince us of the neceſſity of this diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that by it we may chearfully perform our Duty, whilſt we have Liberty and Opportunity; for if we get this, It will quicken us to our Duty, It will aſſiſt us in it, It will make us Patient in waiting for the ſucceſs, which if it do not anſwer our endeavours and deſires, yet the want of ſucceſs ſhall never deprive us of the acceptance of <hi>God,</hi> who in rewarding Miniſters doth chiefly look to this diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; by this means we ſhall be preſs'd in Spirit to our Duty and by doing our Duty, we ſhall Increaſe this diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of mind; <hi>then ſhall we know if we follow on to know the Lord.</hi> Alas! to ſee the world about us lying in wickedneſs, and yet hating to be Reform'd, and hating thoſe that would tell them they have need to Reform. And to ſee the world ſitting in Darkneſs, and yet avoiding the Light, ſhould not this convince us that we have need to get a diſpoſition of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103757:13"/> Mind, that may ſtir us up to do ſomething to amend all this? how little will be done by us without this diſpoſition, ſeeing ſo little is done with it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, <hi>The nature of our Employment and buſineſs, which is to Preach Good Will toward Men, the love of God in giving his Son to dye for us, the love of Chriſt in giving his life for us, doth require a frame of mind ſuitable to the errand that we bring.</hi> If we were to open the <hi>Prophets</hi> Roll in which was nothing but Lamentation and Wo, we were the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, if we did hang back and ſay, <hi>ſend by the hands of him whom thou wilt ſend;</hi> If we had received that meſſage from <hi>God</hi> to you, that <hi>God</hi> delivered to the Child <hi>Samuel,</hi> a meſſage that might make the <hi>Peoples ears to tingle,</hi> and their <hi>hearts to tremble,</hi> we might perhaps lye down again in our ſloth as afraid to deliver it; but this is the meſſage that we bring, that <hi>God</hi> againſt whom man hath Sinned, from whom we have all departed in <hi>Adam,</hi> hath given man, Fallen, Sinfull Man, Eternal life, and this life is in his Son; ſurely ſuch an Employment, to be Meſſengers of ſuch tidings, whatever reception it may meet with from wicked, and unreaſonable Men, doth require in us Miniſters a diſpoſition of mind ſuitable to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Miniſterial work is attended with a peculiar Reward;</hi> there is a Reward peculiar to a Diſciple, and a Reward pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Miniſters; if I ſhould tell you how ſure and certain the Reward is, you might ſay ſo 'tis to all other men, for all Offices of love and Charity, even the Leaſt, <hi>ſo that he that giveth a Cup of cold water to a Diſciple, in the name of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, ſhall Receive a Diſciples reward;</hi> but yet tho' Miniſters have no more certainty of a reward than other Men have, yet they have the certainty of a greater reward, and therefore It is ſet out by the <hi>ſhining of the Sun in the Firmament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103757:14"/>
            <p>Now ſurely ſuch a reward doth require a chearful will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſolute performance of our Duty, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not conditioned upon our ſucceſs in Converting, but our diligence in the performing our Duty; for ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that any Miniſter ſhould not Convert one Soul (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive few that are faithful are ſo unhappy in their labours) yet if it ſhould prove ſo, there is that which may relieve that Miniſter, <hi>We are</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in them that periſh a ſweet ſavour to God.</hi> God that knoweth all Mens hearts doth ſee 'twas what ſuch Miniſters did deſire and endeavour, and God accepts them not according to the ſucceſs, but their deſires and endeavours, to which this diſpoſition is ſo highly uſefull.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Practical Inferences are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This ſhews the Reaſon of our backwardneſs to our Duty,</hi> who is there that hath not his excuſes for his neglects? but the plain truth is all our excuſes and delays do proceed from our unwillingneſs; the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their recovery out of the Captivity, could not deny but 'twas fit that the Temple ſhould be built, but 'twas no fit time to ſet about it, It went hard with them, they were newly come out of the Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they were poor, they had many Enemies, and yet though they could not finiſh the Temple, they had their Ceiled Houſes: now an heart made willing can over-look and deſpiſe greater diſcouragements than we can pretend unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>'Tis not only our Duty to do Well, but to look to the Principle from which every act of Obedience floweth.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome Men, that <hi>to every good Work they are Reprobates,</hi> having neither a Will to, nor a skill in the performance of them, <hi>Titus,</hi> 1.16. and becauſe we are ſo averſe to all that is good, we muſt be <hi>New made, Created in Chriſt Jeſus to good works,</hi> and by this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103757:14"/> you may ſee where our chief care ſhould be, even to that which God chiefly requires, and firſt begins at: thou art troubled at thy performances, I don't utterly diſlike that trouble, but thou had'ſt need to look at ſomething beyond that; thy Nature, that, that be changed, thy Will, that, that be ſubdued, that thereby thou be made <hi>meet for thy Maſters uſe and Service, and prepared to every good work,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.21. to have the fewel is not enough till you have fire to kindle it; without the renewing, diſpoſing Grace of God, we may be conſiderate in our words and actions, and do many things outwardly good and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and yet all this while be deſtitute of that which is ſo ſeldom mentioned in ſome Mens Writings, and ſo oft in the Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> Grace without which men may have a Reſemblance of the Life Spiritual, as the Plant hath of the life Senſitive; many a man may have the likeneſs of the life of God in him, and yet remain in the corrupt ſtate of Nature. So that we ſhould not only take care to do well, but labour for a Mind fram'd to our Duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Have a care of being ſtirred up to your Duty by ſuch Inducements as are ſhort of this willing Mind,</hi> See we to this, that we be ſtirred up from ſomething within us, and that it be not any thing leſs than an heart prompting us to our Duty; that only is well done that is done to the Glory of God; and not upon a deſign, let the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign be what it will, if it be not to pleaſe God, and to be accepted of him, It will leave us ſhort of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reward; for though it hath the appearance of an act of Religion, God Eſteems it not ſo: <hi>have ye faſted unto me?</hi> to faſt for ſtuff, to pray to be ſeen of Men, to give Alms to be applauded, may go a great way in the ſight of Men, who ought to the praiſe action without En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103757:15"/> into the heart, but it hath no other reward than what is here; but he that is prompted to his Duty from his own heart, <hi>hath a Teſtimony in himſelf, in which he may rejoyce.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, <hi>let us all get this Willing Mind, this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing principle,</hi> that what we do may be <hi>accepted</hi> and <hi>Rewarded:</hi> under this head I ſhall ſpeak in the <hi>general to all,</hi> and <hi>Particularly</hi> to my <hi>brethren</hi> in the <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. All of us have need to <hi>Pray</hi> and to be <hi>Inſtant with God</hi> for this <hi>diſpoſition of Mind:</hi> For</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>by this means our Duty will be the more eaſy;</hi> 'tis true Chriſt hath a <hi>Yoak,</hi> and a <hi>Burden,</hi> but there is nothing that tends more to make it eaſy to us,<note place="margin">Motives.</note> than the diſpoſedneſs of our Wills and Hearts unto it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Will being the chief executive faculty, where that is there the delight of the Soul followeth,</hi> and what a <hi>deſirable diſpoſition</hi> will this be when our <hi>Duty</hi> becomes our <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</hi> that as nature hath provided a delight in doing thoſe things that tend to its preſervation, ſuch as is the Saline humour in the Palat, adjoyning it ſelf with our Meat and Drink, ſo when Grace doth furniſh us with a diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Co natural to our Duty, that it ſhall be our Meat and Drink to do Gods Will; How deſireable is ſuch a temper? get me this, and we ſhall find by experience that the <hi>ways of Wiſdom are ways of Pleaſantneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Hereby our Obedience will be more ſteady and even, and we more conſtant and ſtedfaſt in it, Ephraim</hi> is ſaid to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103757:15"/> 
               <hi>as a Bullock that was not accuſtomed to the Yoak, not uſed to work:</hi> now ſuch a Bullock is ſore with his labour, and unskilfull in it, It makes bawks; 'tis in and out; the main and principal reaſon of our uneven walking, is either the want of a will fix'd and determined to its Duty, or not carryed forth with delight in its performance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>Beg this diſpoſition by Prayer, every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift cometh from above,</hi> this eſpecially: if we can do it our ſelves, Incline and fix our Wills to our Duty, our ſin is the greater if we do not; but if we cannot do it of our ſelves (as to be ſure we cannot) our ſin is the greater, that we are not more earneſt and Inceſſant with God to help us. Prayers for the firſt converting Grace, are not alltogether unacceptable to God; <hi>let us have Grace</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) that is, <hi>let us ſeek it that we may have it,</hi> let us Pray that we may obtain it; and indeed if the natural man could be ſuppoſed ſeriouſly and heartily to deſire this Grace, we could not (without wronging of God) ſuppoſe that he would deny him; they that have not higher and ſtronger arguments, may plead from ſuch as they have, their relation to God as the work of his hands, their rational and natural Powers, <hi>thy hands have made me</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſamiſt) give me underſtandng;</hi> beg alſo the continuing and Increaſe of this firſt diſpoſing Grace, that he that hath made the Willing would keep ſo, and make the more Willing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Keep your hearts under a ſenſe of your Duty;</hi> for tho' the ſenſe of Duty may be urg'd upon us by an enlightned conſcience, which will leave us ſhort of a willing Mind, yet 'tis good to feel ſomething in our ſelves pleading Gods right, urging upon us the neceſſity of our obedience; the Apoſtle did ſo, <hi>if againſt my Will a diſpenſation is committed to me:</hi> I muſt do my Duty, Willing or Unwilling it ought to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103757:16"/> be done; though I loſe the reward, God will not loſe his Right.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Do what you can to make your ſelves Willing, and do what you can to keep your Selves ſo,</hi> even in converſion we muſt not expect that becauſe God can, that therefore he ſhould do all, though all that Man; doth in his converſion, doth not make, nor is the reaſon why Grace is effectual in this rather than in that Man, this doth not ſuperſede Mans Duty towards God's Grace; no, but every one ſhould do his own part, we can attend the means and we can conſider and Remember, and though all that do this do not turn to God, yet 'tis the way to it, the <hi>Pſalmiſt thought and turned</hi> and 'tis ſaid <hi>all the ends of the Earth ſhall Remember and turn to the Lord</hi> Pſal. 22.27. and God blames them that <hi>they would not frame their doings to turn to the Lord.</hi> they would do nothing to promote it <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider <hi>what Encouragements you have from a good God, and from a Gracious Covenant,</hi> wherein ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are accepted and involuntary weakneſſes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to them that do their beſt, though it be infinitly ſhort of what is due, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>I will ſpare them as a Man that ſpareth his only Son that ſerveth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And laſtly, <hi>as to my brethren the Miniſters,</hi> all that I have now to ſay is to my ſelf and you thoſe that would know the reaſon of our coming together at this time, It is this that <hi>I</hi> have been all this while ſpeaking to, <hi>viz.</hi> To Stir up one another to the Dutys of our calling, and to promote the neceſſary work of our Miniſtry. I do not pretend to dictate to Miniſters what is their Duty, but yet I conſider that that Miniſter that needs not to be directed what to do, may yet be content to be encouraged, may need it, and will de thankful for it. Even St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf when the brethren from <hi>Rome</hi> came to meet him
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103757:16"/> at <hi>Appij forum</hi> and the three Taverns, <hi>he thanked God, and took courage.</hi> If I could ſo far ſerve my Brethren 'tis what I aim at.</p>
            <p>And truly (whatever our Circumſtances are) we may do well to conſider the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> for our <hi>Encouragement,</hi> that we may have this <hi>Willing Mind;</hi> now the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> through the perverſneſs of ſome Men eſteemed it his Duty not <hi>only to Preach</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but to <hi>do it for nothing.</hi> And yet It was not becauſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was <hi>richer</hi> than <hi>other men,</hi> no, for being an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and having ſuch <hi>a charge</hi> upon him, he would not have <hi>laboured with his own hands for a livelyhood,</hi> if there had not been a neceſſity lying upon him to do both, to <hi>Work</hi> and yet to <hi>Preach;</hi> now thanks be to God our <hi>Circumſtances</hi> are not the <hi>ſame,</hi> and for that reaſon it is <hi>rarely</hi> the <hi>Duty</hi> of a Miniſter to <hi>do</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle did,</hi> who yet ſhews the greateſt <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in his <hi>condition,</hi> and a full <hi>Reſolution</hi> to ſtick to his <hi>Duty, a neceſſity is laid upon me,</hi> and yet he would not be without a <hi>Willing Mind</hi> under that <hi>neceſſity.</hi> And therefore let our Circumſtances be what they will, if we can <hi>get</hi> this <hi>diſpoſition of Mind,</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> it, we ſhall have cauſe to bleſs God that hath not only <hi>put us into the Miniſtry,</hi> but <hi>into our preſent Circumſtances,</hi> and we have reaſon to be ſo <hi>diſpoſed</hi> to our <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>circumſtances,</hi> not only from <hi>the preſence of Chriſt</hi> with us, <hi>as being workers together with him,</hi> but alſo from that <hi>great change</hi> that Almighty God hath made in our Circumſtances, which although they are not <hi>ſuch</hi> as perhaps <hi>ſome</hi> could <hi>deſire,</hi> yet they are not <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they were,</hi> when the Civil Magiſtrate pinch'd ſo hard upon us, as being Inſtigated doubtleſs) by ſuch Men as ſhould rather have <hi>Rejoyced</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was Preach'd, than have <hi>ſtir'd</hi> up adverſaries againſt Us. But now 'tis <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> and let us bleſs God for it, and it being otherwiſe, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to <hi>forget</hi> what is <hi>paſt,</hi> and <hi>together with them</hi> do
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103757:17"/> our part to Raiſe up the Tabernacle of God, and to <hi>bring back</hi> the People from that <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> which hath <hi>Spread</hi> it ſelf among them, and to <hi>Eſtabliſh</hi> them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi> If any of our <hi>Brethren</hi> have done any thing towards the <hi>caſting us out as unfit builders;</hi> if they have done more than became them as <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in <hi>adding</hi> to our <hi>affliction,</hi> let us endeavour to <hi>forget it,</hi> and <hi>Watch</hi> over our own Spirits, that the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> of what is paſt do not <hi>Imbitter</hi> our own Spirits towards them, as theirs <hi>ſeem'd</hi> to be towards us, <hi>good Men in their heats do not enough conſider what manner of Spirit they are of.</hi> Though they (ſome of them) eſteemed us the <hi>Peſts of the Nation,</hi> unfit not only to <hi>Preach,</hi> but to <hi>live,</hi> let us conſider it was but <hi>ſome</hi> of them; for as to many of them, we ought to <hi>Rejoyce</hi> that the <hi>ſame</hi> Chriſt, the <hi>ſame</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is Preach'd to the People that attend <hi>their Miniſtry,</hi> as is Preach'd by us to the People that attend <hi>Ours,</hi> and whilſt the Contention is whoſe <hi>way is beſt,</hi> who do <hi>Preach moſt ſuitably to the deſign</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> let us Remember that <hi>that Miniſter</hi> doth moſt anſwer the <hi>deſign of the Goſpel,</hi> who doth moſt Preach <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> and truly that <hi>Miniſters Charity</hi> is not very <hi>large,</hi> that <hi>limits</hi> the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> to his own <hi>party,</hi> to Men of his <hi>own Mind</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> nor on the other ſide do I eſteem that Miniſters <hi>Charity,</hi> to be <hi>very large,</hi> that can ſee <hi>Idolatry</hi> in every thing that is not <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commanded</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> as if <hi>every fault</hi> that we commit in worſhiping God were of <hi>one ſort and kind,</hi> and that the moſt <hi>Deteſtable,</hi> and <hi>Abominable,</hi> for ſo is <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider we what a Mercy 'tis to have <hi>Liberty</hi> to do our <hi>Duty</hi> in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>quietneſs,</hi> all of us can 't <hi>travel</hi> to find places to Preach in, all are not <hi>Fitted</hi> to endure <hi>noiſe</hi> and <hi>clamour,</hi> but all of us if we can get this <hi>Willing Mind,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:103757:17"/> that was in the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> may find <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place</hi> to do ſome good to the People. <hi>Diſcontent</hi> at our own <hi>condition</hi> general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpringeth from the reflections that we make upon the <hi>condition</hi> of thoſe that are <hi>above us;</hi> now if ſuch thoughts ſhould ariſe, they that <hi>can Conform</hi> have the <hi>advantage</hi> over us, and perhaps many of them do leſs, if their way be by <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> and ours only by <hi>Allowance;</hi> let us conſider, we have more than the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi> liv'd to ſee, for they were never free from Perſecution, any longer than their <hi>Perſecutors</hi> were wearied with their own <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> or <hi>diverted</hi> by other <hi>intervening</hi> occaſions, or <hi>Reſtrained</hi> by Gods <hi>Providence</hi> ſome other way; nay, we have as much <hi>Liberty</hi> as we are <hi>Capable</hi> of at <hi>Preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if they that Conform live in greater plenty, let us watch againſt <hi>Repining</hi> thoughts at that, and ſee to it, that whilſt they (ſome of them) <hi>Melt away</hi> in the midſt of their Plenty, we don't <hi>Pine away</hi> under our <hi>Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to what is paſt 'tis to be conſidered that the hard uſage which ſome Miniſters met with, was not ſo much (if at all) from them that are now eſteemed the leading Men of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Whether they <hi>did</hi> in this <hi>their Duty</hi> that they <hi>did no more,</hi> I cannot ſay; but they did <hi>declare</hi> their <hi>diſlike</hi> of thoſe <hi>Severities,</hi> and were <hi>allways</hi> Men of <hi>Moderation,</hi> and do now <hi>declare</hi> their readineſs to <hi>abate</hi> ſomethings that the <hi>Law requires</hi> of us to the more <hi>Publick exerciſe</hi> of our <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in the <hi>Pariſh Churches;</hi> but theſe <hi>Severities</hi> were <hi>ſet</hi> on <hi>Foot</hi> by Men that <hi>called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and yet deſigned an <hi>accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> with the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> and therefore 'tis no marvel if on that ſcore they had ſo little reſpect to diſſenting Miniſters, or taking them to be a <hi>Party,</hi> that might be <hi>craſh'd</hi> by <hi>Severity,</hi> rather than <hi>made Pliable</hi> to ſuch <hi>a deſign:</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103757:18"/> Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> that doth not only <hi>confeſs</hi> but <hi>Juſtify</hi> ſuch a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> gives a full account of this matter. But now to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay all heats, we may do well to conſider that we have to do with <hi>ſuch</hi> Men that had rather <hi>abate</hi> of what is <hi>Eſtabliſh'd,</hi> than <hi>add</hi> to it, that have owned the <hi>Reformation</hi> to be <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect,</hi> that would not have us go <hi>backward</hi> towards <hi>Rome</hi> to pleaſe the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but <hi>Forward;</hi> now who knoweth what ſuch a temper may produce? In the mean time let us with all <hi>chearfullneſs</hi> attend our <hi>calling,</hi> and perform our <hi>Duty,</hi> and this will carry us againſt our <hi>Diſcouragements:</hi> diſcouragements there will be not only from them that are <hi>againſt us,</hi> but from them that are <hi>with us</hi> and <hi>for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this diſpoſition of mind will help us to weather them out and <hi>perſiſt</hi> in our <hi>Duty,</hi> and to do <hi>what we may,</hi> and <hi>whilſt we may,</hi> I ſay <hi>whilſt we may;</hi> for I am perſwaded that that <hi>Door</hi> of Liberty to do our Duty in <hi>quietneſs</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> which <hi>Divine Providence</hi> hath now of late <hi>opened</hi> ſhall not be <hi>ſhut</hi> again but by our own <hi>negligence</hi> or the <hi>Peoples</hi> unprofitableneſs.</p>
            <p>There are two things that <hi>Miniſters</hi> above <hi>other Men</hi> ſhould <hi>fear,</hi> viz. the <hi>loſs</hi> of the <hi>opportunity for doing their Duty,</hi> and the <hi>loſs</hi> of that <hi>diſpoſition of Mind,</hi> that is neceſſary to its <hi>acceptable performance;</hi> as for the former, the <hi>opportunity</hi> of <hi>doing</hi> our <hi>Duty,</hi> and the <hi>quiet excerciſe</hi> of our <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> 'tis God that <hi>gave</hi> it, nay <hi>wrench'd</hi> it out of the hands of thoſe men that <hi>never</hi> Intended it, and without his <hi>leave</hi> none ſhall <hi>ſhut</hi> this <hi>Door;</hi> as to the latter <hi>a diſpoſition of Mind towards the performance of our Duty,</hi> the preſervation of this is <hi>more eſpecially</hi> our concern, and to ſee that we do not neglect Gods gift in us. God hath been pleaſed of late years eſpcially to enlarge <hi>our opportunities,</hi> and we ſhall have no need to fear the loſs of thoſe whilſt we <hi>diligently attend our Duty;</hi> and God to <hi>prevent</hi> our <hi>fears,</hi> that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103757:18"/> they may not <hi>diſtract</hi> us in our <hi>Duty,</hi> hath as it were ſecured our <hi>Liberty</hi> not only by a <hi>Law,</hi> but by <hi>twiſting</hi> it with the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> So that thoſe <hi>very Men</hi> or <hi>Men</hi> of the <hi>Same Mind,</hi> that before argued for <hi>Severity,</hi> and for a <hi>reſtraint,</hi> from the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to argue for <hi>Liberty,</hi> for <hi>Moderation</hi> from the <hi>ſame Topick;</hi> I do not ſay that the <hi>argument</hi> was well <hi>applyed,</hi> or that it was ever, or ever will be the <hi>real Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> or of any other <hi>Nation</hi> to be <hi>Severe</hi> towards all that <hi>differ</hi> from the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd way:</hi> God in giving Nations <hi>Chriſtian Princes;</hi> doth not give thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> for this Reaſon, becauſe they are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a <hi>Power</hi> to do <hi>Evil;</hi> no; by <hi>being Chriſtians</hi> they have an <hi>advantage</hi> to do the more <hi>Good,</hi> but they have never the more <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> or do <hi>Evil;</hi> but if wiſe Men do ſometimes argue for <hi>Severity</hi> and <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> and in a little time after <hi>againſt Severity</hi> from the <hi>Intereſt of the Nation,</hi> then it follows that either the <hi>Intereſt of Nations</hi> may <hi>Vary,</hi> and ſo Indeed it may, or elſe <hi>Wiſe</hi> Men do <hi>change</hi> their <hi>Minds</hi> and are not <hi>all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways</hi> wiſe; and therefore neither by the one or the other have we any great ſecurity, and it being ſo there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that we can with <hi>more ſafety trust</hi> to under God, than the <hi>diligent performance</hi> of our <hi>Duty,</hi> that will <hi>ſecure</hi> our <hi>Liberty</hi> if any thing ſhall do it; for if we <hi>Willingly diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>painfully</hi> Preach as we are able, and as we have an <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> and a <hi>call,</hi> and yet ſhould happen to be <hi>reſtrain'd</hi> as before, than it will appear that God <hi>took</hi> it from us; but 'tis to be hoped that God <hi>will not,</hi> for <hi>ordinarily</hi> he doth not <hi>puniſh</hi> as a <hi>Soveraign,</hi> but as a <hi>Juſt Judge</hi> provoked by our Sins. The way therefore to preſerve our Liberty is to do our Duty.</p>
            <p>Beſides the <hi>loſing the opportunity,</hi> we ſhould fear to <hi>loſe the Diſpoſition of Mind</hi> to <hi>perform</hi> our <hi>Duty;</hi> this by <hi>Neligence</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103757:19"/> will be <hi>loſt</hi> or <hi>abated,</hi> as <hi>tools</hi> not <hi>uſed</hi> will <hi>Rust,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments</hi> of <hi>Muſick</hi> laid <hi>aſide</hi> will grow out of <hi>Tune,</hi> but if we perſiſt in our Duty, <hi>that</hi> will <hi>diſpoſe</hi> us to it, and by this means our work will be <hi>the more eaſy</hi> and <hi>delightfull</hi> to us; and this is the way to <hi>profit</hi> the People and to be <hi>Succeſsfull</hi> in our labours, for the more we ſtand <hi>affected</hi> to our Duty, the more we ſhall be in <hi>earnest</hi> with the People, without which the Miniſtry <hi>ſeldom</hi> ſucceeds; and then when we can <hi>diſcern</hi> that ſome <hi>Good</hi> is done, that will again <hi>put Life</hi> into us; a <hi>Willing Mind</hi> in the <hi>Minister</hi> is moſt likely to beget a <hi>Willing Mind</hi> in the <hi>People,</hi> and by this means the <hi>one</hi> will mutually aſſiſt the <hi>other:</hi> However, if <hi>ſucceſs</hi> do not <hi>attend</hi> (as alas! it doth not in ſome places) yet there is that which may <hi>relieve</hi> us in that <hi>caſe;</hi> our <hi>reward</hi> is with the <hi>Lord,</hi> to whom, whatever the <hi>Iſſue</hi> be, we ſhall be a <hi>ſweet ſavour,</hi> this is our <hi>last relief,</hi> the eying the <hi>Reward,</hi> the Miniſterial <hi>Reward;</hi> which if we <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>conſider,</hi> will help us to be <hi>Stedfast and unmoveable, and to abound in the Work of the Lord, whilſt we know that</hi> (though as to men it may be much Fruitleſs, yet) <hi>it ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. line <hi>ult.</hi> for <hi>Expoſe</hi> read <hi>Expreſs.</hi> p. 4, l. 30. for <hi>For,</hi> r. <hi>From.</hi> p. 8. l. 9. after <hi>ſtick</hi> add <hi>but.</hi> p. 12. l. 16. after <hi>He,</hi> add <hi>that.</hi> l. 18. after <hi>ſingular</hi> add <hi>or.</hi> p. 13, l. 7. for <hi>When</hi> r. <hi>which.</hi> p. 14. l. 25, for <hi>Swavitys,</hi> r. <hi>Suavitys.</hi> l. 32. after <hi>Neglect,</hi> add <hi>is.</hi> p. 15. l. 17. for <hi>And.</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103757:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
